Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files /3033
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files
1953-1967
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Konvitz, Milton R.
/3033
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Professor Konvitz's files regarding the drawing up of the official body of statutory laws for the Republic of Liberia.
8436109
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 26, 2015
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, October 11, 2022
Biographical / Historical
March 12, 1908 - September 5, 2003
Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School.
Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor.
At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students -Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House.
In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime.
Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher."
Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years.
He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in-law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1945 as the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, the ILR School today is advancing the world of work through teaching, research and outreach. ILR's mission is to prepare leaders, inform national and international employment and labor policy, and improve working lives, but as the world of work evolves, the school's focus broadens to keep pace with that change.
ILR studies many areas that shape the working world and contribute to an organization's success in a global economy. These include human resource management; labor-management relations; labor economics; organizational behavior; international and comparative labor; labor relations, labor law and history; conflict resolution; management development; diversity management; employment and disability; and social statistics.
An ILR education is grounded in the social sciences. Students and faculty explore and gain an understanding of human behavior through the lens of the workplace. Students also learn how organizations work and how they fit into the larger society and economy. As a result, they acquire knowledge and skills that help them to solve problems on- the-job and to build and manage productive work relationships. An ILR education, for students and professionals, is practical and applied.
ILR has more full-time faculty involved in teaching and research that spans the broad range of work and employment disciplines than any other educational institution of its kind. Its Martin P. Catherwood Library is regarded as the most comprehensive source of information in North America on work, employment and labor issues.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers /4341: Milton R. Konvitz Collections
Konvitz, Milton R. (Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003
8436109
- Liberian Codification Project Associations Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality Law, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Maritime Law, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Liberian Codification Project - Maritime Law, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Liberian Codification Project - Labor Laws - Apprentices (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Liberian Codification Project, Maritime Law, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Liberian Codification Project, Injuries Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Liberian Codification Project - Banking and Insurance Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Liberian Codification Project, Public Works Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Liberian Codification Project, Revenue and Finance Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Liberian Codification Project, Revenue and Finance Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Liberian Codification Project, Transportation and Communications Law, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Liberian Project, Vehicle and Traffic Law, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- ABA - Government Employee Relations, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- NEA Position, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- NYS JLC Report, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- The American Labor Movement: Its Historical, Political, and Philosophical Development (Box 1, Folder 18)
- The American Labor Movement: Its Historical, Political, and Philosophical Development, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Scope and Contents
  2 of 2
- Liberian Codification Project - Aborigines Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Liberian Codification Project, Agriculture Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Liberian Codification Project, Civil Procedure Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Liberian Codification Project, Civil Procedure Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Liberian Codification Project, Civil Procedure Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Liberian Codification Project, Commercial Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Liberian Codification Project, Constitution of Republic of Liberia (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Liberian Codification Project, Criminal Procedure, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Liberian Codification Project, Criminal Procedure, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Liberian Codification Project - Criminal Procedure, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Liberian Codification Project, Decedents Estate, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Liberian Codification Project, Domestic Relations, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Liberian Codification Project, Education Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Liberian Codification Project Election Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Liberian Codification Project, Executive Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Liberian Codification Project Executive Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Liberian Codification Project Foreign Relations Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Liberian Project, General Construction Law, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Liberian Project, Judiciary Law, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Liberian Codification Project, Local Government Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Liberian Project Legislative Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Liberian Codification Project, National Defense Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Liberian Codification Project, Natural Resources Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Liberian Codification Project, Patent, Copyright and Trade Mark Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Liberian Codification Project Patriotic Observances Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Liberian Project Penal Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Liberian Codification Project, Postal Service Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Liberian Codification Project, Property Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Liberian Codification Project, Public Employment Law, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Health Safety Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Lands Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Welfare Law, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Index Cards on Legal Codes (Box 3, Folder 1)
  1 of 2
- Index Card on Legal Codes (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Inventory in Safe in Dr. Konvitz' Office in Ithaca (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aborigines Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Liberian Codification Project - Associations Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Criminal Procedure Law (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Election Law (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Liberian Codification Project - Agriculture Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Liberian Codification Project - Aliens Nationality Law, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Liberian Codification Project - Banking and Insurance Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Corrected Pages - Civil Procedure Law (Box 3, Folder 12)
  volume 1
- Civil Procedure Law (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Liberian Codification Project - Civil Procedure Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Liberian Codification Project - Civil Procedure Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Liberian Codification Project - Commercial Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Liberian Codification Project - Constitution of Republic of Liberia, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Liberian Codification Project - Constitution of Republic of Liberia (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Liberian Codification Project - Criminal Procedure, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Liberian Codification Project - Domestic Relations, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Liberian Codification Project - Education Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Liberian Codification Project - Election Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Election Law Material (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Liberian Codification Project - Executive Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Liberian Codification Project - Foreign Relations Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Liberian Codification Project - General Business Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Liberian Codification Project - Labor Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Liberian Project - Legislative Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Liberian Codification Project - Local Government Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Liberian Codification Project - Maritime Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Liberian Codification Project - Natural Resources Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Liberian Codification Project - Patent, Copyright, and Trade Mark Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Liberian Project - Penal Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Liberian Project - Penal Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Liberian Codification Project - Property Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Liberian Codification Project - Property Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Liberian Codification Project - Patriotic Observances Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Liberian Codification Project - Postal Service Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Liberian Codication Project - Public Employment Law, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Health Safety Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Lands Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Welfare Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Liberian Codification Project - Public Works Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Liberian Codification Project - Revenue and Finance Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Liberian Codification Project - Revenue and Finance Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Civil Procedure and Finance Minutes (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Liberian Codification Project - Law of Torts, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Liberian Codification Project - Law of Torts, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Liberian Codification Project - Transportation Communications Law, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Constitution of the Republic of Liberia (Box 3, Folder 49)
  as amended through 1951
- Aborigines Law (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Agriculture Law (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Aliens and Nationality Law (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Associations Law (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Banking Insurance Law (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Civil Procedure Law - Folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Civil Procedure Law - Folder II (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Commercial Law (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Constitution - Republic of Liberia (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Criminal Procedure Law (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Decedents Estates (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Domestic Relations (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Education Law (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Election Law (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Executive Law (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Foreign Relations (Box 4, Folder 16)
- General Business Law (Box 4, Folder 17)
- General Construction Law (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Injuries Law (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Judiciary Law (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Labor Law (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Legislative Law (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Local Government Law (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Maritime Law (Box 4, Folder 24)
- National Defense Law (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Natural Resources Law (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Patent, Copyright Trade Law (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Patriotic Observances Law (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Penal Law (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Postal Service Law (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Property Law (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Public Employment Law (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Public Health Safety Law (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Public Lands Law (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Public Welfare Law (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Public Works Law (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Revenue and Finance Law - Folder I (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Revenue and Finance Law - Folder II (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Transportation Communications Law (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Vehicle Traffic Law (Box 4, Folder 40)